RAMUEL BATUIGAS

(647) 708-0091

ヹ rjbatuigas@gmail.com

in linkedin.com/in/rjbatuigas

• github.com/ManagementEngineer www.ramuel.ca

PROFILE

Ex-Amazon and Engineering Analyst with over 3 years of work experience in data analysis, business intelligence, software development, technical support, and project execution. Knowledgeable across multiple industries including public service, technology, logistics, manufacturing, and transportation, and equipped with a postgraduate certificate in Al Solutions Development.

EXPERIENCE

IT Analyst, Intern

May 2023 - Sept 2023

The Regional Municipality of York

Newmarket, ON

- Provided technical support for systems, subsystems, and technologies for York Region's IT services on hardware and software issues ranging from installation to technical troubleshooting.
- Generated and addressed ITS tickets by systematically reproducing and resolving issues through a series of step-by-step actions.
- Developed an Al-powered question-and-answer chatbot capable of engaging in human-like conversations to efficiently address document-specific inquiries, including eDOCS problem-solving.

Business Data Analyst

May 2021 – Jan. 2023

JC Electrofields Power System Inc.

Manila, PH

- Enhanced decision-making processes by developing more than 10 comprehensive report templates using Excel and PowerBI, facilitating the extraction of actionable insights for strategic guidance.
- Reduced operational and labour costs by 5% by conducting exploratory data analysis to uncover patterns, trends, and anomalies in inventory and labour data.
- Independently executed data cleansing, transformation, and validation processes to enhance data quality and reliability for reporting and analysis purposes.

Area Manager

Feb. 2020 - May 2021

Amazon.com Inc.

Toronto, ON

- Developed an automated reporting tool coded in VBA to reduce report preparation time from 45 min. to 3 min. for daily Parcel-Not-On-Van (PNOV) Reports used by Area Managers across all Canadian delivery stations to analyze and visualize PNOV and contractor performance trends.
- Led the top performing station in the Prime Free Same Day (PFSD) shift across Canada, dispatching twice the normal volume at 3,500 packages daily with a success rate of 98.85%.

Reliability Analyst, Intern

Sept. 2018 - Dec. 2018

Toronto Transit Commission

Toronto, ON

- Analyzed subway door lead-screw fault records by K-means clustering, providing visualizations and categorization
 of subway door fault notifications from 2012 to 2018.
- Eliminated subway door lead-screw re-greasing problems by providing mean time between failures based on Weibull Analysis.

Transit Fleet Analyst, Intern

May 2017 - Sept. 2017

The Regional Municipality of York

Richmond Hill, ON

- Extracted and transformed ad hoc reports by leveraging advanced SQL querying techniques to analyze preventative maintenance data of York Region public transit assets.
- Designed and spearheaded the User Acceptance Testing of York Region's new fleet management system.
- Coordinated with fleet contractors by acting as the fleet management system co-administrator, responsible for technical software troubleshooting and data integrity.

Supply Chain Analyst, Intern

Aug. 2016 - Dec. 2016

Loblaw Companies Ltd.

Brampton, ON

- Reduced manual order rate by 17.37% by proposing new safety stock numbers for Deli products in 3 pilot stores.
- Saved 6 minutes per product analysis by fixing inefficiencies in Loblaw's automated ordering system.
- Corrected the company's overall fill rate calculation by identifying the root cause of a Click-and-Collect system issue.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Languages: Python, DAX, SQL, VBA, JavaScript, HTML/CSS

Developer Tools: PowerBI, Jupyter Notebook, Excel, VS Code, Docker Libraries: pandas, scikit-learn, NumPy, Matplotlib, TensorFlow, PyTorch

EDUCATION

George Brown College

Toronto, ON

Applied A.I. Solutions Development - Postgraduate - Dean's List

Jan. 2023 - Present

University Of Waterloo

Waterloo, ON

Bachelor of Applied Science Honours Management Engineering

Sept. 2014 - June 2019

PROJECTS

Yahoo Fantasy League Dashboard | PowerBI, DAX, Python, API

Oct. 2023 - Present

- Executed a full-stack data analysis project, leveraging four years of Fantasy League data, encompassing data retrieval, transformation, and visualization.
- Utilized the Yahoo Fantasy Sports API and Python to access and preprocess Fantasy League data, ensuring data consistency and quality.
- · Created interactive and informative PowerBI dashboards, delivering valuable insights into Fantasy League trends, manager statistics, and strategic decision-making, ultimately enhancing individual team management.

AdventureWorks PowerBI Dashboard | PowerBI, DAX

Sept. 2023

 Created a complete PowerBI report to track KPIs, compare regional performance, analyze product-level trends, and identify high-value customers based on raw data.

Taylor Swift's Musical Diary: Unveiling Her Emotional Evolution in Lyrics | Python, HuggingFace

Aug. 2023

 Created a Sentiment Analysis of Taylor Swift Songs using Recurrent Neural Network powered by Natural Language Processing models.

DeSouza Institute Smart Course Scheduling Tool | Python, mySQL, PHP, Git

Sept. 2018 - Apr. 2019

- Built statistical analysis models using Operations Research, Linear Regression, and Polynomial Regression to forecast future course enrollment and mixed integer programming scheduling algorithm to maximize revenue.
- Developed a full-stack application using Python and SQL to create an automated scheduling system with integrated optimized algorithms.

CERTIFICATES

Microsoft PowerBI Desktop for Business Intelligence Udemy	Oct. 2023
The Ultimate MySQL Bootcamp Udemy	Sept. 2023
100 Days of Code: The Complete Python Bootcamp Udemy	Nov. 2022
Lean Six Sigma Greenbelt Institute of Industrial Engineers, University of Waterloo Chapter	Sept. 2015
AWARDS	
Cited for Excellence The Regional Municipality of York	2023

kcellence | I ne Regional Municipality of York

Recognized for excellent customer service in supporting a regional staff in technical troubleshooting.

Cited for Commitment | The Regional Municipality of York

2023

Recognized for persistence and diligence in solving client's technical issues.

DEA Site Champion | Amazon.com Inc.

2020

Awarded to the best Canadian delivery station with the highest Delivery Estimate Accuracy.

Cited for Excellence | The Regional Municipality of York

2017

· Recognized for the contribution in the User Acceptance Testing of the new M5 Fleet management system for the Region's critical services.

Best Team | Clearbridge Mobile

2015

Awarded to the best app development team in the company.